<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: coding | Chris Meier's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://ChrisMeier.github.io/blog/categories/coding/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ChrisMeier.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-25T11:13:34-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://ChrisMeier.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chris Meier]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[State your purpose]]></title>
    <link href="http://ChrisMeier.github.io/blog/2013/09/25/state-your-purpose/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-25T09:21:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ChrisMeier.github.io/blog/2013/09/25/state-your-purpose</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, this is my first blog post (outside the traditional hello world), both on this platform and in my lifetime. Being new my first thought is to discuss my intentions for this blog as well as how it came to be so I will answer the latter and then the former so it all makes sense.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>My interest in blogging has been fairly minimal and I chalked it up as a medium for people who had something to say to say it and be heard by the few that found what they had to say of interest. In writing this I realize that not many people will every read this, if any at all, but for the sake of my intentions of creating/writing I will continue.</p>

<p>So why have I put this together? Well that is fairly simply: I needed a platform to document and discuss my movement through learning Ruby on Rails (Note to self: link later when you know how?). After having spent the summer interning at a start-up with development based around Ruby on Rails and having heard such great things about it from classmates I have decided to try my hand at it. In planning my learning of how to code with Ruby on Rails it was recommended that I put together a blog for two reasons. The first being that I have a way of documenting and sharing my progress, the second being that I can have a side project to maintain and update as time goes on.</p>

<p>So, you have a blog, what are you going to do with it?
Well as a mentioned previously my intentions are to practice Rails as this has been coded in Rails but additionally to document my progress. More importantly I see the blog as a platform to share my ideas about what I will be developing (read: trying to develop) and a way to discuss challenges that I have faced and offer insight into a rookies mind while trying to figure out this evidently &ldquo;beautiful&rdquo; language and framework that is Ruby on Rails.</p>

<p>With that said, welcome to Chris on Rails and hear is what you can expect to see soon: <br>
1. Updates to the blog as they come, at an extremely granular level<br>
2. My experience with coding and OO-principles <br>
3. My process for learning rails so far <br></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
