<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: apple | Chris Meier's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://ChrisMeier.github.io/blog/categories/apple/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ChrisMeier.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-28T20:47:53-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://ChrisMeier.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chris Meier]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Alternates to Apple Mail]]></title>
    <link href="http://ChrisMeier.github.io/blog/2013/10/28/alternates-to-apple-mail/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-28T20:28:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ChrisMeier.github.io/blog/2013/10/28/alternates-to-apple-mail</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since upgrading to Mavericks I have found the Apple Mail app to be incredibly buggy. Mail often takes 5-10 minutes longer than it takes for it to arrive on my phone or within the browser client. There are also other instances where the mail process will spike to 200% &ndash; 500% CPU usage according to the iStat Pro widget. This doesn’t effect the performance of the rest of the computer but it is a huge drain on my battery. Additionally, from time to time the fans will spin up to 6000 RPM’s and my normally quiet Macbook Pro is now competing with a professor for the loudest thing in the room.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Alternate 1: Mail Pilot</h3>

<p>Until that is fixed (and I did look to see if there was something I could do) I have chosen to use another mail app. My first choice became the Kickstarter success <a href="http://www.mailpilot.co">Mail Pilot</a>. It is one of those email clients that focuses on turning your email into a to-do list and aims for inbox zero.</p>

<p>The mobile app looks great (at least from the app store pictures) but unfortunately the desktop version is currently in beta and is slow to roll out. So option 1 is on the back burner for now.</p>

<h4>Alternate 2 Part 1: Air Mail</h4>

<p>The next client I came across is called Air Mail. It is a fairly simple looking client with a lot of customization as far as how you want it to look. It is has a clean feel to it but also has a weird color thing going on with the various folders in your mail box.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/Images/BlogImages/AirMailFolders.png" title="&lsquo;image&rsquo; &lsquo;images&rsquo;" >
The speed compared to apple mail is night and day, everything from pulling in mail to opening up a random folder it is incredibly quick. The inbox also has gesture support, two-finger swipe-right to archive and swipe-left trash the item. Bottom line is that Air Mail has a familiar feel compared to Apple Mail but is much quicker and doesn’t kill my battery.</p>

<h4>Alternte 2 Part 2: Mailbox App</h4>

<p>Since Mail Pilot was my first choice I considered getting their mobile app but decided instead to wait for the desktop version before investing $14.99 in their ecosystem. A competitor to Mail Pilot, <a href="http://www.mailboxapp.com">Mailbox</a>, was also picking up a lot of attention and is very similar in functionality so I am currently giving that a shot as well. Mailbox also has a to-do list/inbox zero approach to email and as an added benefit you get an extra 1GB in Dropbox.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
